Guide to the Edwin W. Lynch Vietnam War protest collection, 1965-1975
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Edwin W. Lynch Vietnam War protest collection
1965-1975
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Lynch, Edwin Williams, 1913-2004
C0080
6 linear feet (4 boxes)
The collection provides information on the discontent and disillusionment which came to exist among some segments of the American people as a result of American military intervention in Southeast Asia. The collection covers the period of time ranging from 1965 to 1975, with the bulk of the material from the years 1967 to 1971.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Edwin W. Lynch in 1983.
Biographical Information
Born in Annandale, Virginia, in 1913, Edwin Williams Lynch, a prominent Northern Virginia real estate businessman, served as Fairfax County delegate to the Virginia General Assembly from 1945 to 1947 and again from 1949 to 1954. For more than 50 years, Lynch participated in the George Mason University community. As a George Mason University Foundation trustee and an ICAR advisory board member and chairman, Lynch supported a framework of programs that have ensured a margin of excellence and distinction for ICAR. In 1987 Lynch endowed the first chair and an annual lecture series, in memory of his parents, Vernon and Minnie. The following year, he helped to establish the doctoral program, the first in the world. In 1996, Lynch and his wife, Helen, created the John W. Burton Endowment, named for one of ICAR's most distinguished professors. Lynch died in 2004.
Scope and Content
The collection provides information on the discontent and disillusionment which came to exist among some segments of the American people as a result of American military intervention in Southeast Asia. The collection covers the period of time ranging from 1965 to 1975, with the bulk of the material from the years 1967 to 1971.
The collection consists of a variety of materials relating to the Vietnam War including pamphlets, booklets, correspondence, posters, reprint articles, newspaper clippings, various antiwar publications, and the minutes of meetings of several antiwar groups. These items are arranged by subject heading in alphabetical order, and the material within the individual files is arranged in chronological order. Much of the information contained in the Collection relates to the activities of various groups that were formed to protest the American involvement in Vietnam, groups representing such disparate segments of the population as the clergy and business executives. While this information manages to give us a good view of the antiwar movement in the United States as both a local and a national phenomenon, the collection is particularly valuable for the information it provides on the work of local groups based in and concerned with the Washington D.C. area, including Northern Virginia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by alphabetically by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds other collections with materials on the Vietnam War including the, the, and the
Index Terms
Subjects:
Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Protest movements--United States.
Contents List
- Edwin M. Lynch Vietnam War protest collection
  - American for Democratic Action "World", 5/67, 12/71 (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1/72, 2/72 (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - Anti-Draft Activities (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Activities Within the U.S. Armed Forces, Admirals and Generals opposed to the Conflict in Vietnam (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Activities Within the U.S. Armed Forces G.I.'s opposed to the Conflict in Vietnam (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Activities Within the U.S. Armed Forces G.I.'s opposed to the Conflict in Vietnam ( The "Presidio 29") (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Activities within the U.S. Armed Forces Veterans opposed to the Conflict in Vietnam (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Activities of Religions, Groups (Folder 8, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Demonstrations (Folder 9, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Miscellaneous (Folder 10, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Northern Virginia Coalition to End the Air War (Folder 11, Box 1)
  - Anti-War movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Northern Virginia Moratorium Committee (Folder 12, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Washington Area Peace Action Coalition (Folder 13, Box 1)
  - Anti-War Movement in the Greater Washington Metropolitan Area Washington Peace Center Newsletter (Folder 14, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move For New National Priorities (1974-1975) Formerly Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace (Folder 15, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move For Vietnam Peace Activities Relating to Political Elections (Folder 16, Box 1)
  - Business Executives for Vietnam Peace Efforts to influence the resident and Members of Congress, 10/67 - 3/69 (Folder 17, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Effort to influence the President and Member of Congress, 6/69 - 10/69 (Folder 18, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Effort to influence the President and Members of Congress, 4/70 - 5/72 (Folder 19, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Meetings, 1967,1968 (Folder 20, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move For Vietnam Peace Meetings, 1969 (Folder 21, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Meetings, 1971,1972 (Folder 22, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Miscellaneous, 1067,1972 (Folder 23, Box 1)
  - Business Executive Move for Vietnam Peace Miscellaneous (Undated) (Folder 24, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace "news Notes" (1068,1070, 1968,1970 (Folder 25, Box 1)
  - Business Executive Move for Vietnam Peace "news Notes" (1971) (Folder 26, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace "News Nots" (1972) (Folder 27, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace "New Notes", 1973 (Folder 28, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Participation in Demonstrations for Vietnam Peace (Folder 29, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace Radio and Television Advertisement (Folder 30, Box 1)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace " Reprint Articles" (Folder 31, Box 1)
  - Businessmen Education Fund (1069-1071), 1969-1971 (Folder 32, Box 1)
  - Businessmen Educational Fund (undated) (Folder 33, Box 1)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned (Formerly Clergy and Lay men Concerned about Vietnam) (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report" (12/04/72) (Folder 2, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report" (, 2/26/73, 3/25/73 (Folder 3, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned " American Report", 5/21/73 - 6/18/73 (Folder 4, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 7/2/73 - 7/30/73 (Folder 5, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 8/13/73 - 9/22/73 (Folder 6, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 10/15/73 - 10/29/73 (Folder 7, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 11/121/73 - 12/10/73 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned " American Report", 1/21/74 - 3/18/74 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 4/15/74 - 4/29/74 (Folder 10, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 5/13/74 - 6/10/74 (Folder 11, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 7/8/74 - 7/22/74 (Folder 12, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned "American Report", 9/15/74 - 11/26/74 (Folder 13, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned Washington Area Chapter (Folder 14, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen (Folder 15, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 10/70 (Folder 16, Box 2)
  - Concerned about Vietnam Anti-Ballistic Missile opposition (Folder 15, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report"i, 12/70 (Folder 16, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 11/70 - 12/70 (Folder 17, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 1/71 - 2/71 (Folder 18, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " American Report", 3/71 - 7/2/71 (Folder 19, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 7/9/71 - 10/6/71 (Folder 20, Box 2)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 10/15/71 - 11/5/71 (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 11/18/71 - 11/25/71 (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " American Report, 1x/71 (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 1/21/72 - 2/4/72 (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " American Report", 2/11/72 - 2/25/72 (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned " American Report", 3/3/72 - 3/24/72 (Folder 6, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American rEPORT", 3/31/72 - 11/21/72 (Folder 7, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " American Report", 4/28/72 - 5/26/72 (Folder 8, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "American Report", 6/2/72 - 6/23/72 (Folder 9, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " American Report", 6/30/72 - 9/1/72 (Folder 10, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam Amnesty for draft resistors (Folder 11, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam Demonstrations for Peace (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam Fact Sheets on War (casualty figures, troop withdrawal, information, etc..) (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam Honeywell Inc. (Protests against) (Folder 14, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Issues and Actions" (Newsletter of 10/68 - 6/69), 10/68 - 8/69 (Folder 15, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Issues and Actions" (newsletters of 11/69 - 6/70) (Folder 16, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "Memoranda and news notes, 10/27/67 - 12/9/68 (Folder 17, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Memoranda", 1/14/69 - 5/16/69 (Folder 18, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "Memoranda", 7/18/69 - 9/9/69 (Folder 19, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Memoranda, 10/1/69 - 11/21/69 (Folder 20, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " memoranda", 1/7/70 - 6/12/70 (Folder 21, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam "Miscellaneous", 1967 - 1973 (Folder 22, Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Miscellaneous" (undated) (Folder 1, Box 4)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Poster Service", 3/69 - 3/70 (Folder 2, Box 4)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Poster Services", 4/70 - 9/70 (Folder 3, Box 4)
  - Clergy and laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Reprint Articles', 1967 - 1968 (Folder 4, Box 4)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Reprint Articles", 1968 - 1970 (Folder 5, Box 4)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam " Statements of Position (Folder 6, Box 4)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam Virginia activities (Folder 7, Box 4)
  - Committee of Responsibility to save War-buried and injured Vietnamese children (Folder 8, Box 4)
  - Congress of the united States Congressional Record, 4/67 - 5/70 (Folder 9, Box 4)
  - Congress of the United States Individual Members of Congress (Folder 10, Box 4)
  - Congress of the United States Miscellaneous (Folder 11, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace, 1967 - 1068 (Folder 12, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Business Executive s Move for Vietnam Peace, 1968 (Folder 13, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace, 1969 (Folder 14, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace, 1970 - 1975 (Folder 15, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Clergy and Laity Concerned (Folder 16, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam (Folder 17, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Letters to the editor, 1967 (Folder 18, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Letters to the editor, 1968 (Folder 19, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Miscellaneous, 1967 (Folder 20, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Miscellaneous, 1958 - 1969 (Folder 21, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Miscellaneous, 1970 - 1974 (Folder 22, Box 4)
  - Rett Dorr, 1/67 - 7/67 (Folder 23, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Reverend Everett Dorr, 8/67 (Folder 24, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Reverend Dorr, 10/67 - 12/68 (Folder 25, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch Reverend Everett Dorr, 1969 -1071 (Folder 26, Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Edwin Lynch SANE (Folder 27, Box 4)